בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is נ"ג nun gimel fifty-three,
we're a little behind. We pick up on נ"ב עמוד ב' nun
bet amud bet at the משנה. mishna. We just finished going through
the נשרפים nisrafim and how it's about really pouring this molten lead,
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has it being tin or sulfur or something down
somebody's throat, and learning about from כעין מיתה, ke'ein misa, like a
natural death.
So now we move on to the next משנה mishna in the
middle of נ"ב עמוד ב', nun bet amud bet, the middle of
נ"ב עמוד ב' nun bet amud bet right there before the line
get wide. מצות הנהרגים. Mitzvas haneheragim. How about the what's called הרג,
hereg, which is actually like a, you know, but it's death by
the sword. היו מתיזין את ראשו בסייף. Hayu matizin es rosho besayif.
They would decapitate him with a sword. כדרך שהמלכות עושה, Kederech shehamalchus
osa, like the government, like the Roman government does. רבי יהודה אומר
Rabbi Yehuda omer. ניוול הוא לו, nival hu lo, this is a
disfiguring of the body. אלא, Ela,
what rather the way they would do it is, מניחין את ראשו
על הסדן, manichin es rosho al hasadan, they would put his head
on the chopping block on the, I guess it's called an anvil,
right? וקוצץ בקופיץ, vekotetz bekuppitz, and they chop it off with an
axe. אמרו
לו, Amru lo, אין מיתה מנוולת מזו, ein misa menuvelet mizu, there's
no greater
disfiguring death than this. You're so concerned that disfiguring, how is this
any less disfiguring, which is a good question. So let's see in
the גמרא. Gemara. But I do want to say something about the
issue about כדרך שהמלכות עושה. Kederech shehamalchus osa. So I did a
little research about Rome and how they would execute people. So apparently,
again, I am no expert, this is from five minutes of research
on the web. But apparently crucifixion was something that was mostly reserved
for non-citizens.
For citizens who were executed, it was by the sword. But apparently
initially it seems like in early Roman history it was by the
axe, exactly what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying. But then they
decided that that was not as honorable of a death as by
the sword. So actually those two types of execution,
the axe and the sword, were both used by the Roman government,
but apparently they settled on the sword, at least this is what
I've been able to find out, they later moved to the sword
because that was seen as a more respectful death. I guess because
you know, sword is what you use in battle and so on,
so maybe it little bit echoes that. An axe is more like
what you do for inanimate things or for animals. So whatever it
was, they moved to the sword, which is what the, which is
what the rabbi say, כדרך שהמלכות עושה. Kederech shehamalchus osa. Okay, so
let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תניא, Tanya, אמר לו רבי יהודה לחכמים, amar lo Rabbi
Yehuda lachachamim, so how did רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda respond to the
חכמים chachamim because they made a good point, an axe is pretty
disfiguring too, or even more disfiguring. So he said to them, אף
אני יודע שמיתה מנוולת היא. af ani yodeia shemisa menuvelet hi. I
also know that an axe is a disfiguring type of a death.
אבל מה אעשה שהרי אמרה תורה, Aval ma e'eseh sheharei amra Torah,
what choice do I have? The תורה Torah says ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו,
uvchukoseihem lo seleichu,
don't go in their laws, don't go in their ways. And therefore
I can't do an execution that is the type of execution that
the secular government does. Because that would be seen as mimicking the
secular government. And therefore I'm going to choose this, so it's very
funny, why did you use the word ניוול? nivul? Maybe it's a
ניוול nivul to be cause it it evocative of the idea like
if you're being executed by the government and it removes the religious
context of it, maybe that's why he used the word ניוול, nivul,
right? Somebody at least they want to get executed in בית דין,
beis din, they don't want to be treated like some Roman,
like somebody who's being executed by the Romans. So it is funny
his use of the word ניוול, nivul, but what this תוספתא Tosefta
makes clear, this ברייתא braisa makes clear, is that his real concern
was is that we cannot do it in a way that it
parallels what's being done by the Roman government.
So רבנן, rabbanan, and again it's interesting because again by the little
history that I was able to find out and share with you,
the axe was also done by the Roman government, but presumably that
was in the past. And right now to use a sword would
be seen like the type of death by the execution by the
government. And that would be inappropriate. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבנן,
rabbanan, what do the רבנן rabbanan answer back? Don't they agree to
this prohibition ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו? uvchukoseihem lo seleichu? So they would say,
כיון דכתיב סייף בתורה, keivan dechsiv sayif baTorah, since the תורה Torah
speaks of execution by the sword. Now we haven't seen what this
is based on, where does the תורה Torah ever speak about execution
by the sword, where is this execution in the תורה, Torah, but
we will see it. Since it's based on the תורה, Torah, לא
מינייהו קא גמרינן. lo minaihu ka gamrinan. We're not learning from them.
Okay, so sometimes our practices parallel their practices. That's not a prohibition
ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו, uvchukoseihem lo seleichu, that's just coincidence. We're not doing
it as a way of learning or mimicking them. Maybe it's evocative
of what they do, but that's not the reality. The reality is
that this is an internal type of a practice. אי לא תימא
הכי, Had lo teima hachi, if you don't say that, הא דתניא
hadetanya שורפין על המלכים ולא מדרכי האמורי. sorefin al hamelachim velo midarchei
ha'emori. You can have these funeral pyres when a king dies, you
know, and burn all of their effects, and it's not considered to
be an Amorite practice, which either means like an idolatrous practice or
a pagan practice or just means a like, you know, a practice
of the non-Jews even if it's not an idolatrous concern. You know,
an exact, it's not a concern of בחוקותיהם. bechukoteihem. It's not seen
as, "Oh, how can you do that? That's a גויש goyish thing
to do." So it's not a problem. היכי שרפינן? Heichi sarfinan? Now
how do we do that? והכתיב Ve'hachtiv ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו. uv'chukoteihem lo
telechu. If you have to say it's not מדרכי האמורי, midarchei ha'emori,
it means that it is paralleling the practices of the pagans, we're
just saying it's not a problem. Right? If actually the pagans weren't
doing this, you wouldn't have to tell me it's not a pagan
practice. What you're telling me is that even though pagans do the
same thing, it's not forbidden on account of it being a pagan
practice. So why not? Isn't it the same thing that the pagans
do? So the גמרא Gemara say, so אלא כיון דכתיב שריפה באורייתא,
ella keivan de'chtiv sreifa b'Oraita,
but because there is in the תורה Torah this idea of having
these burning the effects of a king when they die. דכתיב, De'chtiv,
as it says, ובמשרפות אבותיך uv'misrefot avoteicha
and in the burnings of your forefathers that came before you, you
also will have a similar type of a funeral pyre. So you
see that it's in תנ״ך Tanakh already, this idea that this was
a practice. Okay, of course we are bracketing the idea that maybe
it was adopted in the period of תנ״ך, Tanakh, you know, from
the surrounding nations. Okay, we're bracketing that. Since the תורה Torah or
the נביאים Nevi'im or whatever give validation to it, it shows that
it's recognized as an acceptable Jewish practice, and since that's where we
sort of derive it from, and so therefore לא מינייהו קא גמרינן.
lav minaihu ka gamrinan.
We're not learning from them, so it's not a problem of בחוקותיהם
bechukoteihem if it mimics what they're doing as long as it's not
derived and it's not a mimicking of. Meaning if it parallels what
they're doing but it is not a mimicking of them, it is
not learning from them and doing it, you know, in a way
and having that as the source of it, it is not a
problem of בחוקותיהם. bechukoteihem. So this is very interesting in terms of
what are the parameters of בחוקותיהם, bechukoteihem, right? Is it all about
intent? You know, is it all about like, you know, I mean
is it enough? Does it have to be written in the תורה
Torah or let's say it's just a reality that this just was
an internal Jewish development and, yes, I'm doing this but I'm not
doing it with the intent of being like them. You know, I'm
just so, like that becomes very interesting types of questions. You know,
some ראשונים Rishonim of course say like, oh, should we not דאוון
daven because the גויים goyim דאוון? daven? Should we not, you know,
what are the types of things? Let's say if Jews go to
visit graves? Right? Oh, maybe it should be אסור assur because the
גויים goyim go to visit graves. Well, are we learning from them
or are these just parallel developments? Right? So these are like the
types of questions. Now, the other factor that gets thrown in, and
we're not going to have a whole שיעור shiur in בחוקותיהם bechukoteihem
although it's a fascinating topic, but the other factor that gets thrown
in is what is if it
specifically touches on things which are seen as inherently reflective of the
non-Jewish, you know, the idolatrous world that we are trying to reject
some of its ethos? Meaning if it's not just an arbitrary practice.
How do you execute? They execute, we execute. Right? Okay, so we're
not learning from them, it doesn't start from them. But specifically the
two things that the ראשונים Rishonim mention specifically are things that have
to be, that are sourced in עבודה זרה, avoda zara, okay, and
things that are sort of deal with like a sort of promiscuous
sexuality, you know, that those types of things it might not matter
whether we're mimicking them, doing it for the intent of mimicking or
not doing it for the intent of mimicking, those things might more
inherently be labeled as בחוקותיהם, bechukoteihem, representing a sort of, you know,
a pagan or non-Jewish ethos and therefore problematic. Anyway, but that becomes
very interesting, exactly figuring out what those parameters are. Yes. Isn't it
problematic anyway because there is a... right, but the question is, let's
say they began in that area, but that, so the whole question
becomes like can you wear like certain, you know, when I was
graduating from high school, the big question was, "Can we wear the
graduation robes which are sourced in priestly garb and this and that?"
You know, even though now they're no longer about that. Right? So
those are like, so these are the types of discussions. Anyway, this
is a very important source for discussions of בחוקותיהם. bechukoteihem. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was bothered
with him and he wanted a different type of an execution.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, דהא דתנן דאידך פרקין, d'ha detnan d'idach pirkin, אלו הן הנהרגים,
elu hen ha'neheragin, the following are the people that we execute by
the
sword, הרוצח ואנשי עיר הנדחת, ha'rotzeach ve'anshei ir ha'nidachat, the murderer and
the people of the whole city that worship עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
So now we're going to start looking at this idea. How do
we know who gets this type of execution and how do we
know that the תורה Torah actually tells us to do this type
of execution? So בשלמא עיר הנדחת כתיב. Bishlama ir ha'nidachat ktiv. So
עיר הנדחת ir ha'nidachat is the one explicit thing. It says you
should kill all of them לפי חרב, lefi charev, by the edge
of the sword. By the way, that could have been an even
better response that the חכמים Chachamim could have said to רבי יהודה:
Rabbi Yehuda a hatchet isn't a sword. Which always raises the interesting
question about how precisely do we think the Torah is dictating, you
know, what to do? Like, okay, we learned that it's supposed to
be a שריפה sreifa internal, but, you know, does it have to
be lead? Can it be other ways of doing it? You know,
what are our range of options? It doesn't seem—it seems like there's
a, you know, some parameters, but within the parameters we can maybe,
you know, it's not hyper-precise. So לפי חרב lefi charev apparently for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda: includes a hatchet, but the rabbis read it
as a sword. Anyway, that's why that's explicit.
אלא רוצח, Ella rotzeiach, but a murderer, that's the only other one
who gets executed by the sword. מנלן, Minalan, where do you know
it from? דתניא, De-tanya, we learn in a ברייתא, braisa, נקם ינקם,
nakom yinakeim, right, this is by killing a slave.
כי יכה איש את עבדו Ki yakeh ish es avdo whatever,
ומת תחת ידו נקם ינקם. u-meis tachas yado nakom yinakeim. Hit a
servant and a slave, actually, this is a tremendous חידוש chidush of
the Torah, that a person can actually kill a slave, not even
with the intent to kill him, it seems like from the פשט,
pshat, sounds like they were just trying to beat them, but anyway,
kill a slave and actually be executed. That a owner free man
would be executed by killing a slave, a non-Jewish slave, right, עבד
כנעני eved kenaani is the way the rabbis understand it, you know,
what that does to recognize the humanity of the slave is pretty
astounding for, you know, for the ancient world. Anyway, that's in the
Torah, okay, so that's the only other place it says נקם ינקם,
nakom yinakeim, should take vengeance. נקמה זו איני יודע מה היא, Nekima
zo eini yodeia mah hi, I don't know what this vengeance means.
כשהוא אומר והבאתי עליכם חרב נקמת נקם ברית, Keshehu omer veheiveisi aleichem
cherev nokemes nekam bris, when it says in the קללה, klala, I'll
bring against you a sword that takes vengeance of the covenant,
הרי אומר נקמה זו סייף, harei omer nekimah zo sayif, so you
see נקמה nekima is associated with the sword. So that's how I
know that that also gets the sword. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואימא דברזי מברז, ve-eima de-varzei mi-vraz, maybe it doesn't mean—maybe it should
mean rather than you use—you do a cutting motion, maybe you should
do a stabbing motion. Okay, maybe you should like, you know, pierce
the guy through the—through the stomach or something like that or pierce
him in the heart. So it says ואימא דברזי מברז, ve-eima de-varzei
mi-vraz, so it says לפי חרב כתיב, lefi charev ksiv, no, by
the edge of the sword, meaning the cutting motion, not a—what? פי,
Pi, like the mouth.
Right, the mouth. Right. So it means the lip or whatever, it
means—it means the—so it's a cutting motion, not a stabbing motion. ואימא
דעביד ליה גיסטרא, Ve-eima de-avid lei gistra, maybe you should slice him
not at the neck, maybe you should just like slice him lengthwise
or slice him widthwise. Okay, אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה
אמר קרא ואהבת לרעך כמוך. amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha
amar kra ve-ahavta le-reiacha kamocha.
Once again, so powerful, we're always quoting that פסוק, pasuk, even when
we're executing this person and doing this horrific type of an act
of violence, we have to respect him and do it in the
most,
you know, in the—in the most respectful way possible. ברור לו מיתה
יפה. Berur lo misa yafa. So it's obviously much less disfiguring and
probably painful to the body, you know, because it's probably more immediate
if you cut them at the neck than if you, you know,
try to slice them lengthwise or something. Okay. So עד הכא דקטיל
עבדא עבדא. ad hacha de-katil avda avda. Now that's if somebody kills
a slave. בן חורין מנלן? Ben chorin minalan? How about if you
kill a—a free person? ולא קל וחומר, Velo kal vachomer, what's the
קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Because by other—normally when it speaks about killing
somebody, it says that the person is executed, and we're going to
find out that execution without being specific is חנק, chenek, is strangulation.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know,
why—maybe it should just be strangulation for killing a free person. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ולא קל וחומר, velo kal vachomer,
what's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? קטיל עבדא בסייף, Katil avda besayif,
if you kill a slave you get the sword which is a
weightier execution than strangulation. So בן חורין בחנק? ben chorin bechenek? So
should you think that if you kill a free person it's a
lighter form of execution? No, of course it would be the weightier
execution of the sword. So הני ניחא למאן דאמר חנק קל, hani
nicha le-man de-amar chenek kal, that's good for the one that say
חנק chenek is the lightest. אלא למאן דאמר חנק חמור, Ella le-man
de-amar chenek chamur, but according to רבי שמעון Reb Shimon that says
חנק chenek is weightier than the sword, מאי איכא למימר, mai ika
le-meimar, what can you say? Maybe for a free person you should
get חנק chenek if that's weightier execution. So נפקא ליה, nafkalei, so
we learn it from דתניא ואתה תבער הדם הנקי מקרבך. de-tanya ve-ata
teva'er hadam hanaki mikirbecha. This is again about executing the murderer. You
should destroy, you should cleanse yourself from the innocent blood from your
midst. So it's a very generic פסוק pasuk about how you deal
with murderers. So הוקשו כל שופכי דמים לעגלה ערופה—regular, hukshu kol shofchei
damim le-egla arufa excuse me, that's not by a murderer, excuse me,
that's by the עגלה ערופה, egla arufa, that's by when you don't
know who—I mean it is a murderer, but not executing the murderer,
it's when you do the ritual of the עגלה ערופה, egla arufa,
okay. And it says that you should go ahead and cleanse the
spilled blood. So the ritual of the עגלה ערופה egla arufa is
being linked to the general idea of dealing with murderers, of cleansing
the land from the blood. So הוקשו כל שופכי דמים לעגלה
ערופה. hukshu kol shofchei damim le-egla arufa. מה להלן בסייף, Mah lahan
besayif, the same way you, you know, you chop the head of
the calf with a sword, ומן הצוואר, u-min hatzavar, and from the
neck, אף כאן בסייף ומן הצוואר. af kan besayif u-min hatzavar. here
too with a sword and by the neck. So basically now the
link starts being a לימוד limmud from נוקמת נקם ברית nokemet nakam
brit and more the paradigm is עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah. And that
allows us to include at least all murderers, not just the murderer
of the slave, but all murderers based on the paradigm of עגלה
ערופה. Eglah Arufah. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, אימא להלן
בקופיץ וממול עורף, eima l'halan b'kofitz u'mimmul oreph, but there it's maybe
that's actually a good source for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda because there
you use a hatchet and you do it by the back of
the neck, not by the throat. So it's actually it's not an
exact paradigm except maybe according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda, So אף
כאן בקופיץ וממול עורף, af kan b'kofitz u'mimmul oreph, maybe here you
should do the same? אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר
קרא ואהבת לרעך כמוך, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar
kra v'ahavta l'reiacha kamocha, בר לו מיתה יפה. bor lo mitah yafah.
Yes, even if עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah is our paradigm, we don't
feel that it's hyper-specific, and we feel that it gives us a
basic sense of death by the sword, but we can work within
those parameters. Okay, so again interesting how ואהבת לרעך כמוך v'ahavta l'reiacha
kamocha plays a role in figuring out the exact parameters. Okay, so
that is סייף, sayif, הרג. herag. Now we move to the last
one, which is חנק, chenek, which is the generic one. מצות הנחנקין,
Mitzvat hanechenakin, how would they do strangulation? היו משקעין אותו בזבל עד
ארכובותיו, Hayu mashki'in oto b'zevel ad arkubotav, it's very similar to how
they would do the שרפה sreifah except it would they would not
end with the pouring of the molten lead. They would put him
up to his knees in this dung, apparently to help keep him
steady, okay, ונותן סודר קשה לתוך הרכה, v'noten sudar kasheh l'toch harakah,
they would put a
wrap a soft scarf around a harder rope, וכורך על צוארו, v'korech
al tzavaro, and wrap it around his neck, זה מושך אצלו וזה
מושך אצלו, zeh moshech etzlo v'zeh moshech etzlo, each one pulls you
know two ends are pulled in the opposite direction, עד שנפשו יוצאת,
ad she'nafsho yotzeit, until he dies through strangulation. Okay, and again the
reason of the wrapping of the soft thing is that it should
not be as painful and should not be as disfigured. תנו רבנן,
Tanu rabbanan, the Rabbis taught, איש פרט לקטן, ish prat l'katan, okay,
so this is a first it's a פסוק passuk about committing adultery,
which is going to be one of the sort of bases for
talking about death by strangulation. It's one of the cases that it
is death by execution by strangulation. So first we parse the פסוק
passuk about the prohibition. It says איש אשר ינאף את אשת איש,
ish asher yinaf et eishet ish, if a man commits adultery with
a married woman. So איש, ish, if a man commits adultery, פרט
לקטן. prat l'katan. If it's a minor, then you're not going to
execute a minor for sin, which is true in general. The interesting
thing is that according to the גמרא Gemara actually if a married
woman sleeps with a boy over the age of nine, even if
he's not בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, even if the boy is not
executed, it's still considered an act of adultery from the married woman's
perspective and she is still executed. So although this might make it
sound like if the if the if the if the man is
underage, nobody has sinned, like it's a it's not true. It means
the man isn't punished, but if he's enough of an age that
it's considered an act of intercourse, the woman would still be punished.
אשר ינאף את אשת איש, Asher yinaf et eishet ish, that commits
adultery with a married woman, פרט לאשת קטן, prat l'eishet katan, to
exclude a the wife of a minor. Now how do you have
a wife of a minor? You the woman could be a minor,
she'd be married off by the father, but קידושין kiddushin has to
be done by by the man, and the man has to be
an adult. So how could you ever have a wife of a
minor? So רש״י Rashi says this is just telling you that fact.
It's telling you that there is no הלכתי halakhic קידושין kiddushin with
a minor boy, and therefore that's why you're exempt, because it wasn't
adultery, because it wasn't a binding קידושין. kiddushin. תוספות Tosafot actually says
I can find you a way that you could have binding קידושין
kiddushin with the with a minor boy. You know how? יבום. Yibum.
יבום. Yibum. If
it if the brother died, and the brother was married to this
woman, the brother was an adult, and now the boy, יבום yibum
is effected not through a formal act of a קנין kinyan which
requires an adult, but through an act of intercourse. And if the
boy is older than nine, it's considered an act of intercourse. So
therefore if a nine-year-old boy has intercourse with his sister-in-law, his dead
brother's wife, right, actually הלכתית halakhically they would be
married, but but what this is teaching you is it's not a
real enough marriage because he's a minor, meaning it might be like
a legal marriage but it's not a you know a marriage to
a minor is not really real enough, so somehow that is nevertheless
the per you know as long as the kid is a minor
presumably it would change once he hits בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, but
it would not be considered an act of adultery. Okay, so פרט
לאשת קטן. prat l'eishet katan. אשת רעהו, Eishet rei'eihu, אשר ינאף את
אשת איש אשר ינאף את אשת רעהו, asher yinaf et eishet ish
asher yinaf et eishet rei'eihu, the פסוק passuk continues, his fellow's wife,
פרט לאשת אחרים, prat l'eishet acherim, which is excluding the case of
the wife of others, others here means non-Jews. Okay, so if you
commit adultery with a married non-Jewish woman, הלכתית halakhically that is not
an act of adultery. Now non-Jews themselves in terms of the laws
of בני נח Bnei Noach have prohibitions of adultery, right? A non-Jew,
it's considered a violation of the laws of בני נח Bnei Noach
if a non-Jew sleeps with a non-Jewish man sleeps with a married
a married non-Jewish woman. But from the perspective so marriage is meaningful,
like is recognized
Wait, I'm reading this as like, I thought it was a Jewish
woman marries a non-Jew.
That is also correct. Yes, both of those are correct.
Okay? That but that in a certain way is more obvious
that you're correct. That's true similar to the קטן Katan that marriage
is not binding between a Jewish woman and a non-Jew. So that's
an easier point as it were. Right, that's correct. I think רש״י
Rashi says it. רש״י Rashi says, where's רש״י? Rashi? רש״י Rashi says
פרט
לאשת אחרים, Prat l'Eshes Acheirim, now כותי, Kusi, this רש״י Rashi has
been censored, okay, it was not כותי, Kusi, it was גוי, Goy,
okay, אשמעינן שאין קידושין לגוי, Ashmienan she'ein kiddushin l'Goy, okay, ומהכא תיפוק
ליה. Um'hacha tipok lei.
Now does that mean that a Jewish woman isn't married to a
non-Jew? Or does, right, that's certainly what Jenna says is certainly the
first point, that if it's a Jewish woman to a non-Jew, it's
not a binding קידושין. Kiddushin. If you look at תוספות, Tosfos, פרט
לאשת אחרים Prat l'Eshes Acheirim again he has היינו כותי, Hainu Kusi,
it's not כותי, Kusi, it's גוי. Goy. וקמשמע לן דאין אישות וכו'
לגוים. Vekamashma lan de'ein ishous v'chulu l'Goyim. אף על גב דאין מיתה
ואזהרה, Af al gav de'ein misah v'azharah, איסורא מיהא איכא. Issura meiha
ika. מיהא דאיצטריך למישרי יפת תואר. Miha d'itztrich l'mishrei yefas to'ar.
But now look how he continues. Even though it's not a violation
of adultery, it's still, there's still some prohibition. How do you know?
Because the Torah had to allow the case of the יפת תואר,
Yefas To'ar, the beautiful woman taken captive, and where we teach אשת
אפילו אשת איש, Eshes afilu eshes ish,
that even if this beautiful woman who's taken captive, we just read
it in last week's פרשה, Parsha, is married,
the Torah is still allowing it. Are you with me here? So
that is a case of a non-Jewish woman married to a non-Jewish
man that this Jewish person
captures in battle. And the fact that the Torah had to give
special allowance even though she's married shows that the fact that she
is married, although it's not adultery for a Jew, would still be
considered a problem, whatever that problem would be. There's still some prohibition
around it. So you see Jenna how תוספות Tosfos is implicitly talking
about the marriage of a non-Jewish woman to a non-Jewish man. So
both of those are being said, okay, so
there's a bigger חידוש Chiddush in the case of a non-Jewish woman
to a non-Jewish man because that is a legally recognized marriage, especially
from within the world of בני נח. Bnei Noach. And nevertheless, it's
not adultery from the Jew's perspective. All right, so all this is
quite fascinating, not our issue about מיתת בית דין, Misas Beis Din,
but quite fascinating in its own regards. Okay. Now getting to our
punchline. מות יומת, Mos yumas, they should be surely put to death,
בחנק, B'chenek, with strangulation. אתה אומר בחנק או אינו אלא אחת מכל
מיתות האמורות בתורה. Atah omer b'chenek o eino ela achas mikol misos
ha'amuros baTorah. Maybe it's one of the other things that's more explicit
because the Torah never explicitly even talks about strangulation. אמרת כל מקום
שנאמר מיתה בתורה סתם, Amarta kol makom shenemar misah baTorah stam, אי
אתה רשאי למשוך להחמיר עליה אלא להקל עליה. Ei atah rasha'i limshoch
l'hachmir aleha ela l'hakel aleha. If the Torah just says to execute
and doesn't say how, you have to assume that it's the most
lenient form of execution. You're not entitled to impose on this person
a weightier form of execution. So you have to read it in
the most lenient form. Now of course it's all very nice, but
how do we still know that חנק Chenek is an option? And
how do we know that חנק Chenek is lenient? All right. So
דברי רבי יאשיה, Divrei Rabbi Yoshiyah, that's what רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiyah
says. רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonasan omer, לא מפני שקלה, Lo mipnei
shekalah, it has nothing to do with the fact that we consider
חנק Chenek to be the most lenient. The גמרא Gemara is going
to say he might hold like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that maybe
it's not the most lenient. Okay, so forget that. That's not what
it's based on. אלא, Ela, here's what it's based on. כל מיתה
אמורה בתורה סתם אינה אלא חנק. Kol misah amurah baTorah stam einah
ela chenek. We just know that it's חנק, Chenek, not because it's
lenient. How do we know it's חנק? Chenek? So רבי Rebbe explains.
רבי אומר, Rebbe omer, נאמר מיתה בידי שמים Ne'emar misah bidei shamayim
because it uses the word מות יומת. Mos yumas. מות יומת Mos
yumas is not shall be executed, מות יומת Mos yumas is like
a word of death, dying, dying is a word that's used by
natural death. Okay. נאמר מיתה בידי שמים, Ne'emar misah bidei shamayim, it
talks about natural death, ונאמר מיתה בידי אדם, V'ne'emar misah bidei adam,
מה מיתה אמורה בידי שמים מיתה שאין בה רושם, Mah misah amurah
bidei shamayim misah she'ein bah roshem, the same way natural death there
is no disfiguring of the body, and you don't see any mark
on the body, אף מיתה אמורה בידי אדם מיתה שאין בה רושם.
Af misah amurah bidei adam misah she'ein bah roshem. Here too no
disfiguring. So I guess the point is that even though the other
things, right, סקילה Sekilah is you push the guy down,
שריפה Sreifah is you pour the lead down his throat, maybe it's
not as obvious, שריפה Sreifah certainly it does pretty horrific things inside
the body, סקילה Sekilah presumably still there's some sense of the impact,
you would see some mark, but it's understood I guess if you
do חנק Chenek the right way that you don't even see any
mark. It looks as natural as possible. Even more than that what
you could say is, remember the גמרא Gemara before when it spoke
about שריפה, Sreifah, spoke about חטאו אל גופו ונפשו תמה ונפש. chat'u
el gufo v'nafsho tamah v'nefesh. So חנק Chenek is like death by
strangulation is death by inability to breathe. So it really is the
type of a death that directly attacks your
נפש. Nefesh. Your נפש Nefesh particularly is the word from like וינפש
Vayinafash to breathe and so on. So it's a type of death
that's the most mimicking natural death. There's no disfiguring and it's about
taking the wind out of the person, the breath, the נפש nefesh
out of the person. So that's how we learn it out and
it's not because of oh it's the most lenient, maybe it's not
the most lenient, but the word מיתה misah means the most natural
type, the one that most mimics natural death. So again, this is
one of Dvorstaimetz's points that it is not about some reverence for
the human body. I mean, okay we do have reverence for the
human body, but it's not about that, it's not about the אין
בו רושם ein bo roshem meaning which do you emphasize? אין בו
רושם ein bo roshem because we really care about not disfiguring the
human body and that's a value in itself, or אין בו רושם
ein bo roshem because that's similar to מיתה בידי שמים misah bidei
shamayim that we want it to be as close to possible as
to divinely ordained death. Right? So that's two different way important different
ways of thinking about this. Alright, so anyway it continues. ואימא שרפה,
ve'eima sreifah, so the גמרא gemara says or ואי- מיתה שאין בה
רושם, misah she'ein bah roshem, אף מיתה המסורה בידי שמים מיתה שאין
בה רושם. af misah hamesurah bidei shamayim misah she'ein bah roshem. ואימא
שרפה? ve'eima sreifah? How about burning? Because we said burning at least
leaves the way we do burning leaves the outside unmarred even though
the inside is pretty destructive. So מדאמר רחמנא בת כהן בשרפה, mide'amar
rachmana bas kohen bisreifah, no no no, since the בת כהן bas
kohen gets שרפה, sreifah, clearly that is a heavier punishment and that's
as opposed to the סתם stam death of a normal woman who
commits adultery or man, מכלל דהא לאו בת שרפה היא. michlal deha
lav bas sreifah hi. From here we see the standard adultery is
not שרפה, sreifah, it's a special it's a special punishment for the
adultery of a בת כהן. bas kohen. Okay, so that's what we
learn. Either מיתה misah means as most like a natural death or
somehow it just is generic, so we're going to say it's the
most lenient. So now let's look at the גמרא, gemara, top of
נג עמוד א. nun gimmel amud aleph. בשלמא דרבי יונתן כדקא מפרש
טעמא, bishlama derabbi yonasan kidka mefaraish ta'ama, so we get רבי יונתן.
rabbi yonasan. רבי rebbi explains his reasoning: the word מיתה misah means
the most natural type of looking death.
אלא רבי יאשיה ממי דבמחנק הוא? ella rabbi yoshiya mimay debachenek hu?
For רבי יאשיה rabbi yoshiya said oh it has to be the
most lenient so it's going to be חנק. chenek. How do you
even know that חנק chenek is an option? Where do you even
know there's an idea of חנק chenek as one of the executions?
ואימא סייף? ve'eima sayaf? Maybe it'll be a sword? Because maybe we
only have three? Who says we have four? אמר רבא ארבע מיתות
גמרא גמירי להו. amar rava arba misos gemara gemiri lehu. No, we
have a tradition that there are four executions, so we know by
tradition that this fourth one is חנק chenek and once we know
that that's true by tradition and presumably so therefore we've already have
the other three assigned, so we're going to assume that the generic
one is going to be the most lenient one. Okay, somehow maybe
the tradition also tells us right that this is the most lenient.
So let's take a look at רש"י. rashi. ארבע מיתות. arba misos.
רש"י rashi says three lines down from the top: בשמן הנקוב להן,
bishman hanakuv lahen, meaning it's not only we know that there are
four, we know which four they are, four specific ones. וכיון דלא
פירש למאן נתנה חנק, vikeivan dela pairaish leman nattanah chenek, and since
the תורה torah never tells you, it tells you who gets חרב,
cherev, who gets סקילה, skilah, who gets שרפה, sreifah, never tells you
who gets חנק, chenek, אחר כך קלה היא מכולן, achar kach kallah
hi mikullan, והניחו לסתומות, vehinnichu listumot, שאין רשאי למשוך להחמיר. she'ein rashai
limshoch lehachmir.
So we have no... it never tells us who gets חנק, chenek,
and we also have this whole big category of executions where it
doesn't specify. So we're going to connect the dots and we're going
to say those things it doesn't specify must be because it's the
most lenient by not specifying it's telling us that we don't have
a right to give a weighty execution, we have to give the
most lenient. The one thing we don't know about is who gets
חנק, chenek, so we'll assume this whole group gets חנק chenek and
that חנק chenek is the most lenient. Okay and that's how we
sort of settle on that. Alright. אמר רבא amar rava says רבא.
rava.
I'm
sorry, we just did that.
Okay, גמרא גמירי להו. gemara gemiri lehu. וממאי דלחנק דקלה? umimay delachanek
dekallah? Now when the one says that it's not the most lenient
or it's not because it's the most lenient, it's because that's what
the word מיתה misah means. Okay, so וממאי דלחנק דקלה? umimay delachanek
dekallah? קמיפלגי בפלוגתא דרבי שמעון ורבנן. kamiflagi befalugta derabbi shimon verabbanan.
That's a debate of רבי שמעון rabbi shimon and רבנן. rabbanan. If
you say it's the most lenient then you assign the generic ones
to חנק chenek as the most lenient. If חנק chenek isn't the
most lenient, the way you make the link is because you say
it's similar to the idea of מיתה. misah. It's not about it
being lenient, it's about it being similar to the idea of מיתה.
misah. Okay. Now the גמרא gemara says like this. אמר ליה רבי
זירא לאביי. amar leih rabbi zeira le'abbaye. רבי זירא rabbi zeira said
to אביי, abbaye, שאר הנסקלין דלא כתיב בהו. shear haniskalin dela ketiv
behu. Now this next passage is going to be about how do
we know who gets סקילה? skilah? We're done looking at the way
in which the ארבע מיתות arba misos are done and now what
the next set of משניות mishnayos are going to be doing is,
now that we've described the four executions, let's talk about which sins
get which execution. And the next משנה mishnah if you just jump
your eyes down to like the second wide line: אלו הן הנסקלין,
eilu hein haniskalin, the following are the people who get סקילה: skilah:
הבא על האם ועל אשת אב haba al ha'eim ve'al eishet av
and now we're going to say here's all the people who get
סקילה, skilah, here's all the people who get שרפה, sreifah, here's all
the people who get you know who get הרג hereg etc. So
this next passage in the גמרא, gemara, I gotta tell you, in
my opinion, should have appeared after the משנה. mishnah. This next passage
of גמרא gemara is really no longer talking about what we've discussed
before and is really reflecting on the discussion that gets introduced in
the משנה, mishnah, coming up משנה mishnah in terms of who gets
סקילה. skilah. Okay. I blame it on the printer, you know, because
I think in the original גמרא gemara like it wasn't like that,
the משנה... mishnah... was embedded in the גמרא. Gemara. Like, I don't
know if people know this, but in early printings of the גמרא,
Gemara, it basically looked like now what we have for the גמרא
Gemara and רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosfos. Early printings of the גמרא
Gemara basically had the משנה Mishna here.
You had the משנה, Mishna,
and then you had the גמרא Gemara around it like this,
because the גמרא Gemara was a commentary on the משנה. Mishna. Okay,
and then what the printer anyway embedded it within the primary central
text. So I actually think this next passage belongs after the משנה.
Mishna. Anyway, let's read it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר
ליה רבי זירא לאביי Amar lei Rabbi Zeira le-Abaye שאר הנסקלין דלא
כתיבו סקילה Sha'ar ha-niskalin delo ksivu skila דגמירי מאוב וידעוני. degmiri me-Ov
ve-Yidoni. So we're going to find out that the paradigm for סקילה
skila is אוב וידעוני, Ov ve-Yidoni, which are these types of necromancy
and, you know, these types of ways of raising the dead and
so on. So it says there explicitly that they get סקילה. skila.
Okay, and that's going to serve as the basis to understand everybody
who gets סקילה. skila. Now we're going to... there are two sets
of key words that is used in the פסוק pasuk of אוב
וידעוני. Ov ve-Yidoni. It says מות יומתו דמיהם בם. mos yumasu dmeihem
bam. Okay, they shall surely be put to death, their blood is
on their head. And that combination of words מות יומתו דמיהם בם
mos yumasu dmeihem bam appears in a number of different sins. By
אוב וידעוני Ov ve-Yidoni it explicitly says that they get סקילה, skila,
okay, and with those phrases מות יומתו דמיהם בם. mos yumasu dmeihem
bam. So we're going to use those key words to say any
time it says those words, we're going to say learn from אוב
וידעוני Ov ve-Yidoni that they get סקילה. skila. Everybody get that? Okay,
so here's his question. Which of those words are critical? The מות
יומתו mos yumasu words or the דמיהם בם dmeihem bam words? Because
in most of the other cases it says both, but there are
cases where it only says one. All right, so this is what
he asks. שאר הנסקלין דלא כתיבו סקילה, Sha'ar ha-niskalin delo ksivu skila,
all the cases where we stone where it doesn't say it explicitly,
דגמירי מאוב וידעוני degmiri me-Ov ve-Yidoni and we learn it out from
אוב וידעוני. Ov ve-Yidoni. במה גמירי, Bemai gmiri, what phrase do we
use to extend the סקילה skila from אוב וידעוני? Ov ve-Yidoni? במות
יומתו גמירי Bemos yumasu gmiri the phrase they shall surely be put
to death, okay,
או בדמיהם בם o bidmeihem bam or their blood is on their
head. Now by the way, I should say we just learned before
that when it just says מות יומת, mos yumos, right, that's actually
חנק. chenek. So it's not a big difference from מות יומת mos
yumos to מות יומתו, mos yumasu, just so there's talking about one
person or multiple people. So you'd rather learn it from a more
distinctive phrase, right? So but anyway, but often those two phrases come
together. Which is the key one?
גמירי. Gmiri. אמר ליה בדמיהם דמיהם בם גמירי. Amar lei bidmeihem dmeihem
bam gmiri. We learn it from the word of דמיהם בם. dmeihem
bam. דאי במות יומתו De-ee bemos yumasu if מות יומתו mos yumasu
were the key phrase,
so גמירי gmiri דמיהם דמיהם למה לי, dmeihem dmeihem lamah li, meaning
what would be the purpose of saying דמיהם בם? dmeihem bam? If
דמיהם בם dmeihem bam is a very strange phrase, so if we
say that phrase carries with it the meaning of סקילה, skila, we
understand why it says it by these wide range of sins. But
if it doesn't carry with it the meaning of סקילה, skila, that
we learn from מות יומתו, mos yumasu, what's the point of דמיהם
בם? dmeihem bam? So the גמרא Gemara says okay, flip the question.
אלא מאי בדמיהם דמיהם בם גמירי, Ela mai bidmeihem dmeihem bam gmiri,
דמיהם dmeihem carries the meaning of סקילה? skila? So מות יומתו למה
לי, mos yumasu lamah li, so then why do I need the
phrase מות יומתו? mos yumasu? Make up your mind! One of those
phrases has to be teaching something else. So no, כי תניא ki
tanya that I've got an answer for you. Ah, you've asked the
right question. I was waiting for that question. Here's the answer. מות
יומת המכה רוצח הוא mos yumos hamakeh rotzei'ach hu he shall surely
be put to death, he is a murderer, which by the way
this is not סקילה. skila. This is מות יומת mos yumos and
רוצח rotzei'ach remember is הרג. hereg. Anyway, what does מות יומת mos
yumos tell me? אין לי אלא במיתה הכתובה בו. Ein li ela
be-misah haksivah bo. I only know that you're empowered to execute him
with the assigned form of execution, which by the רוצח rotzei'ach would
be actually the sword. בו מנין שאם אי אתה יכול להמיתו במיתה
הכתובה בו שאתה ממיתו בכל מיתה שאתה יכול להמיתו. bo minayin she-im
ee atah yachol la-hamiso be-misah haksivah bo she-atah memiso be-chol misah she-atah
yachol la-hamiso. How do I know that you have a license if
for whatever reasons, like the guy's getting away and we have to,
you know, shoot after him, or maybe for whatever reason anyway we
don't have the option of using the standard execution, how do you
know in those cases you have a license to use another form
of execution? תלמוד לומר מות יומת המכה Talmud lomar mos yumos hamakeh
מכל מקום mi-kol makom he shall surely be put to death. You
gotta get make sure you execute him one way or another, so
if you can't do it the right way, do it anyway. Okay,
so that's what we learn from מות יומת mos yumos that we
have this broader license. Now that's an interesting question. Do we have
this broader license by everybody who's liable to death penalty or just
by the people for whom it says מות יומת? mos yumos? Okay,
we'll bracket that for now, but the point is מות יומת mos
yumos does teach me something. It teaches me this broader license to
execute in other ways if I need to. So I can understand
דמיהם בם dmeihem bam tells me סקילה skila and מות יומת mos
yumos gives me this broader license. But if מות יומת mos yumos
tells me סקילה, skila, I wouldn't know what to do with דמיהם
בם. dmeihem bam. Okay, so אמר ליה... amar lei... So, אמר ליה
רב אחאי מדפתי לרבינא. Amar lei Rav Achai mi-Difti le-Ravina. ואי במות
יומת קאמרי. Ve-ee be-mos yumas kamiri. So it seems like that's where
we're going. We want to say it's דמיהם בם Demeihem bam and
that מות יומת, Mos yumas, which is a very distinctive phrase, and
מות יומת Mos yumas is giving me this license. So now he
says, he's going to ask the counterfactual. ואי במות יומת קאמרי, Ve-ee
be-mos yumas kamiri, מאי קא קשיא ליה? mai ka kashya lei?
So okay, what would bother you if you learned, besides the fact
that you don't want דמיהם בם Demeihem bam to be superfluous, what's
troubling you about the possibility of using the מות יומת Mos yumas
as the basis for סקילה? Skila? So there's something deeper troubling you.
You know what's troubling you? אילימא אשת איש קא קשיא ליה, Ilima
eishet ish ka kashya lei, לימטי וליגמר מות יומת מאוב וידעוני, leimati
ve-ligmar mos yumas me-ov ve-yidoni, מה להלן בסקילה אף כאן בסקילה. ma
ha-lan bi-skila af kan bi-skila. The problem is that מות יומת Mos
yumas is not as distinctive as דמיהם בם. Demeihem bam. מות יומת
Mos yumas appears by a wider range of things. So maybe where
we're getting at is we don't want מות יומת Mos yumas to
be the key phrase. Because if מות יומת Mos yumas was the
key phrase, we'd be giving סקילה Skila to people you're not supposed
to give סקילה Skila to. Okay? So for example, by adultery, it
says מות יומת, Mos yumas, we just quoted that, and that's חנק.
Chenek. So we can't have מות יומת Mos yumas be the phrase
to mean סקילה Skila because then we would wind up giving סקילה
Skila by adultery, and we know that's not true. You got the
point? It says by the case of the אוב וידעוני. Ov ve-yidoni.
What's the פסוק? Pasuk? ואיש או אשה כי יהיה בהם אוב או
ידעוני... Ve-ish o ishah ki yiheyeh va-hem ov o yidoni...
I could actually look up the פסוק. Pasuk. Does it quote the
whole פסוק Pasuk
there? It's okay. I found it here.
What is it? 20:27. ויקרא Vayikra 20:27. ואיש או אשה כי יהיה
בהם אוב או ידעוני
מות יומתו באבן ירגמו אתם דמיהם בם. Ve-ish o ishah ki yiheyeh
va-hem ov o yidoni mos yumatu ba-even yirgemu otam
demeihem bam. So it's not מות יומת. Mos yumas. Oh, מות יומתו.
Mos yumatu. Okay. So this is אוב וידעוני. Ov ve-yidoni.
What was it?
מות יומתו באבן ירגמו אתם. Mos yumatu ba-even yirgemu otam. So
that's סקילה, Skila,
right? סקילה. Skila. דמיהם בם. Demeihem bam. So we're going to use
either this phrase or this phrase to communicate in other in other
things the idea of סקילה. Skila. So which one is it? So
the first point we made is we want it to be דמיהם
בם Demeihem bam to carry the meaning of סקילה Skila and מות
יומת Mos yumas can carry in other things another meaning, giving greater
license to execute when סקילה Skila doesn't work. But now we're saying
maybe there's some other reason why we really want דמיהם בם Demeihem
bam to be the סקילה Skila phrase. Because דמיהם בם Demeihem bam
is a more distinctive phrase. It only appears by a small number
of things. If מות יומת Mos yumas carried the meaning of סקילה,
Skila, we'd have a question, because then there'd be a number of
sins that we should be giving סקילה Skila to, because it says
מות יומת Mos yumas by things that we know you don't give
סקילה Skila to. One of them we just quoted: adultery. So that
seems to be the deeper thing that's bothering you. You don't want
it to be this because that would then apply סקילה Skila to
other things that we shouldn't be applying it to. So let's take
a look at that. Okay. אילימא אשת איש קא קשיא ליה, Ilima
eishet ish ka kashya lei, if the case of adultery is what's
bothering you, לימטי וליגמר מות יומת מאוב וידעוני, leimati ve-ligmar mos yumas
me-ov ve-yidoni, why don't we learn by adultery from the מות יומת
Mos yumas of
אוב וידעוני? Ov ve-yidoni? מה להלן בסקילה אף כאן בסקילה. Ma ha-lan
bi-skila af kan bi-skila. So now, I have an answer to that.
מכדי אמר רחמנא ארוסה בסקילה מכלל דנשואה לאו בסקילה. Michdi amar rachmana
arusah bi-skila miklal de-nesuah lav bi-skila. I could have got out of
that. מות יומת Mos yumas does mean סקילה, Skila, but in this
case I know not, because I know that it's only the weightier
cases of adultery that get סקילה, Skila, the ארוסה. Arusah. So by
inference, I would understand that a normal case of adultery is not
סקילה. Skila. So maybe מות יומת Mos yumas means סקילה, Skila, but
by the case of adultery I would figure out that it meant
something else. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so that shouldn't
bother you. Maybe the next- maybe this is what's bothering you. אלא
מכה אביו ואמו קא קשיא ליה. Ela makeh aviv ve-imo ka kashya
lei. How about hitting a father and a mother where it says
מות יומת Mos yumas and it's חנק Chenek and it's not סקילה.
Skila. Okay. And maybe that's bothering you. לימטי וליגמר מאוב וידעוני. leimati
ve-ligmar me-ov ve-yidoni. So why not learn from אוב וידעוני? Ov ve-yidoni?
So that's why you feel מות יומת Mos yumas can't mean סקילה,
Skila, because then it would imply סקילה Skila by hitting a father
or mother. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, I got an
answer to that. אטו דגמיר מאוב וידעוני ליגמר מאשת איש. Atu de-gamir
me-ov ve-yidoni ligmar me-eishet ish. דהי איתרשיי למשכא להחמיר או להקל. De-hi
itrashya le-mashcha le-hachmir o le-hakal. I just showed you that we would
know by אשת איש, eishet ish, right? It says איש אשר ינאף.
Ish asher yinaf. Right? The פסוק Pasuk we just read is, you
know, איש אשר ינאף את אשת איש, ish asher yinaf et eishet
ish,
את אשת
איש, et eishet ish, אשת איש, eishet ish, מות יומת הנואף והנואפת.
mos yumat ha-no’ef ve-ha-no’afet. והנואפת. ve-ha-no’afet. Okay. So I just said maybe
מות יומת Mos yumas means סקילה. Skila. Here I'll know it doesn't
mean סקילה Skila by contrast to the case of the נערה מאורסה.
na’arah me’orasah. Okay, so that'll tell me that this one doesn't mean
סקילה. Skila. So now is this one the here by contrast to...
That after the נערה המאורסה, Na'arah Hame'orasah, this means חנק. Chenek. So
now when I'm trying to figure out by אביו ואמו, Aviv v'Imo,
אביו ואמו, Aviv v'Imo, it says אשר יקלל ומות יומת, asher yekalel
v'mot yumat, so I shouldn't be bothered, oh, maybe it should be
סקילה, Skila, and, you know, because I would have an answer. I'll
just learn it out from the more lenient one. Here ומות יומת
mot yumat means חנק. Chenek. So ומות יומת mot yumat can carry
the meaning of סקילה. Skila. Okay, here it won't mean it by
contrast to נערה המאורסה, Na'arah Hame'orasah, and therefore here it won't mean
סקילה Skila because I'll just learn it out from the more lenient
case. So why not say ומות יומת mot yumat means סקילה Skila
and I'll still be able to explain why these two cases don't
get סקילה? Skila? Okay, because this is by contrast to נערה המאורסה
Na'arah Hame'orasah and this because of learning it out from the אשת
איש. Eshet Ish. So it says, why wouldn't you apply any type...
That's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. The גמרא
Gemara is going to say, wonderful, you've now shown that if you
wanted to start with this סקילה Skila because you make this חנק
Chenek in all other cases it'll mean חנק Chenek because we'll always
learn it out from the more lenient. So that's why this can't
mean סקילה Skila because either everything is going to be סקילה Skila
or everything else is going to be חנק. Chenek. Okay, you're not
going to do what you want to do. That's exactly what the
גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה שאני
דהכא ופויה קקשיא ליה. amar lei shari deka v'ufai kakasheh lei.
No, what bothered him is how do you know everybody else gets
סקילה? Skila? Okay, דאי ממות יומת גמירי, d'ei me'mot yumat gamiri, because
if you're going to learn it out from
ומות יומת, mot yumat, אדגמירי מאוב וידוני ליגמר מאשת איש, ad de'gamiri
me'ov v'yidoni ligmor me'eshet ish, let's just learn from אשת איש Eshet
Ish that everybody gets חנק. Chenek. Okay, so the bottom line is
that ומות יומת mot yumat appears in non-סקילה Skila cases, and דמיהם
בם dmeihem bam only appears in סקילה Skila cases. So it's much
easier to say דמיהם בם dmeihem bam means סקילה, Skila, which is
a much more distinctive phrase, okay, and also you get the image,
right, if you're stoning people, if you were to literally stone them,
blood would be flowing out of their wounds. So the דמיהם בם
dmeihem bam is like more literal about what that is. Okay, and
and therefore that means סקילה Skila and ומות יומת mot yumat just
tells you you have a license to execute in other ways if
you can't execute in the right way. Okay, so that is that.
Now that, as I said, really is a commentary on the next
משנה. Mishna. So let's read the next משנה. Mishna. ואלו הן הנסקלין.
V'eilu Hein Haniskalin. Now that we're done with the four types of
execution, we're going to say who gets what. And by the way,
I would tell people who are trying to understand, like, what is
the logic about who gets what, there are a couple of רש"יs
Rashis on this משנה Mishna that try to explain a certain logic
behind why these are the ones, these these are the sins that
get this punishment. So the following ones get סקילה: Skila: הבא על
אם, Haba Al Eim, ועל אשת האב, v'al Eshet Ha'av, or a
man who has intercourse with his mother, the man and the mother,
okay, and again the basic way we learn all of this out
is from דמיהם בם. dmeihem bam. Now we've already know what the
basis is, because either it says it explicitly or it says דמיהם
בם. dmeihem bam. Okay, so a son and a mother, ועל אשת
האב, v'al Eshet Ha'av, or a stepmother. Okay, so a lot of
them are the sexual sins, ועל הכלה, v'al Hakallah, a daughter-in-law, ועל
הזכור, v'al Hazachar, a man, ועל הבהמה, v'al Habeheimah, with an animal,
והאשה המביאה את הבהמה עליה. v'ha'ishah hameviah et habeheimah aleiha. So either
a man having intercourse with an animal or a woman having intercourse
with an animal.
So those are like sexual sins, okay, so those are seen as,
now not all sexual sins, some sexual sins of
כרת. Kares. Some aren't even the death penalty. But the ones that
are, but here are ones that are the death penalty and are
the weightiest death penalty. Okay, then we get to like ones that
are about like attacking God. והמגדף, v'Hamigadef, you know, a blasphemer, ועובד
עבודה זרה, v'Oveid Avodah Zarah, an idolator, והנותן מזרעו למולך, v'Hanoten Mizar'o
l'Molech, giving over your kids to the מולך, Molech, which we'll see
later how much is this considered a form of worshipping idols or
it seems like it's something distinct here because it's not included in
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. ובעל אוב וידוני, Ub'al Ov v'Yidoni, like which
we just mentioned, that's the paradigm, right, the necromancer and so on.
So, you know, so that's not exactly about worshipping other gods, but
it's still about these like other forces and not having faith in
God and so on, right, because the פסוק Pasuk says ואתה לא
כן נתן לך ה' אלוהיך, v'atah lo kein natan lecha Hashem Elohecha,
you don't have to try to predict the future by these types
of things, you know you have prophets, you have faith in God
and so on. Okay, so there's all these things which are much
more God-related. ומחלל את השבת, v'Amchalel et haShabbat, okay חילול שבת, Chilul
Shabbat, which based on, you know, how we've internalized, you know, it's
actually a debate in the גמרא, Gemara, but that חילול שבת Chilul
Shabbat is as weighty as עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, that could be
seen as similar to that
category. והמקלל אביו ואמו, v'Hamkalel Aviv v'Imo, cursing out father and mother.
So here רש"י Rashi gives a reason, right, because maybe he's bothered
not just why does it get סקילה, Skila, but why does it
get סקילה Skila and wounding a mother and a father gets חנק,
Chenek, right? That's the high- the weightiest to the lightest. So רש"י
Rashi says here החמיר מבמכה משום דאיכא תרתי, hichmir mibemakah mishum de'ika
tarti, קלון אביו ואמו, kalon aviv v'imo, a disgracing of, of mother
and the father, ומוציא שם שמים לבטלה, umotzi shem shamayim l'vatalah, and
and using God's name, sort of like using not only saying God's
name for naught, but actually making God and God's name complicit in
this act of disrespecting the parents which are supposed to be about
respecting God. You know, if you think about it, the funny way
that a person is חייב chayav for cursing God, is they actually
have to use God's name to curse God. You know, basically it's
not only saying God should smite God is the act of like
cursing God, right? So by מכה אביו ואמו, maka aviv veimo, you
know, if you say מקלל אביו ואמו, mekalel aviv veimo, God should
curse, whatever, the mother or the father, and mother and father is
sort of a seen as a type of representing the honor of
God. It's very parallel to that act of cursing God. Okay, הבא
על נערה מאורסה. haba al na'ara me'orasa. Now it's interesting, after we
mentioned the sexual sins above, we're now going to mention, those were
more like incest-related, or not incest, I mean, but whatever, it's funny,
it's different, seen as a different category. Some are incest, some, you
know, you have the male, you have the animal, whatever, so it's
obviously not limited to that, but all of those are seen as
different from acts of adultery. So that, and it's but still funny,
it's a big gap. We have all these other things and then
we return to the sexual sin here of adultery. Okay, והבא על
נערה מאורסה, ve-haba al na'ara me'orasa, but again not all adultery, only
a young maiden in who is betrothed. Now back we keep on
moving back and forth between like idolatry-related stuff and sexual-related stuff. והמסית
והמדיח, ve-hamasit ve-hamadiach, the one who seduces an individual to commit idolatry,
that's the מסית, masit, והמדיח ve-hamadiach is the one who makes a
whole city or town commit idolatry. והמכשף, ve-hamachashep,
the person who does witchcraft. It's very funny, right, these seems like
we're repeating the same groupings, but we should have organized the sexual
ones together and these idolatry and witchcraft ones together. Okay, רבי יהודה
אומר. Rabbi Yehuda Omer, Okay, ובן סורר ומורה. u-ven sorer u-moreh. Okay,
that's one that doesn't fit exactly, but maybe it does fit. Maybe
that's evocative of like the מקלל אביו ואמו. mekalel aviv veimo. So
we now have these three things: sexual sins, idolatry, and parents. But
we go through the list twice. You see how we have the
same type of categories but we go through, it's very strange. Somebody
will explain this to me. Okay. Anyway, והבא על ה-... ve-haba al
ha-... now, now that's we're done with the list. Those three categories
gone through twice. Now we're going to go back and look at
them individually. הבא על האם
חייב עליה משום אם ומשום אשת אב. haba al ha-em chayav aleiha
mishum em u-mishum eshet av. If a man has intercourse with his
mother, who's also his father's wife, if it's actually if they're married,
then he's he's liable for two sins: mother and father's wife. Now,
of course you can't kill a person twice, but the relevance is,
well, I guess the relevance first of all is let's say you
warn him about one of those and not the other, so it's
considered a legitimate warning because he got because he's doing both sins,
so you can warn him about either. Or if he does it
unintentionally, he would bring two קרבנות korbanot as opposed to one. They're
considered two separate sins because you can have one without the other.
You can have a father's wife who's not a mother, and a
mother who's not a father's wife, and if she happens to be
both, then you then you have done both sins. Okay, רבי יהודה
אומר אינו חייב אלא משום האם בלבד. Rabbi Yehuda omer eino chayav
ela mishum ha-em bilvad. No, when it's both, it's only defined as
the sin of the mother and not the sin of the father's
wife. Father's wife meaning for Rabbi Yehuda the word father's wife means
stepmother. It doesn't mean anybody who's anybody who's the father's wife. It
means father's wife who's not your mother. Okay, so if she's your
mother, she's not in the father's wife category. והבא על אשת אב,
ve-haba al eshet av,
now somebody has intercourse with his father's wife, חייב משום אשת אב
ומשום אשת איש. chayav mishum eshet av u-mishum eshet ish.
And if the father is still alive, and this would obviously be
true about the mother as well, but we wanted to focus on
the debate of Rabbi Yehuda there. If the woman is still married,
in addition to mother and father's wife, you could also be a
married woman, so three death penalty sins. Okay, of course if they
only warned him about the אשת איש eshet ish issue, he would
get חנק chenek and he wouldn't get, you know, סקילה sekilah and
so on, or she would only get it. בין בחיי אביו ובין
לאחר מיתת אביו. bein bechayei aviv uvein le-achar mitat aviv. Now, this
does not mean the married woman. Married woman status is only while
the father is alive and still married to her. If he dies
or divorces her, she stops being a married woman. But the prohibition
of father's wife is even if he's no longer the father's wife,
even if she was once the father's wife, even if he's dead,
she still is prohibited because he was the she had been the
stepmother. בין בחיי אביו ובין לאחר מיתת אביו. bein bechayei aviv uvein
le-achar mitat aviv. בין מן האירוסין בין מן הנשואין, bein min ha-eirusin
bein min ha-nisuin, whether she was married with אירוסין eirusin just the
betrothal or whether they was נשואין nisuin whether they actually lived together.
הבא
על כלתו, haba al kalato, a man who has intercourse, by the
way, of course all of these are said from the male perspective,
it doesn't say a woman who has sex with her son, a
woman who has intercourse with her father-in-law, it's all the man's perspective,
which is the way it is in the Torah. Okay, so a
man who has intercourse with his daughter-in-law, חייב עליה משום כלתו, chayav
aleiha mishum kalato, he transgresses daughter-in-law, ומשום אשת איש, u-mishum eshet ish,
if she's still married to his son, then it's these
double. But even if the son dies or divorces her, she's still
forbidden as daughter-in-law. בין מן האירוסין בין מן הנישואין bein min ha-erusin
bein min ha-nisuim and regardless of how that marriage was effected, whether
it was at the first stage or the second. Okay, so first
the whole list and then looking at the individual cases. So now
that the גמרא, Gemara, this just proves that I'm right by the
way, that the earlier discussion belonged after the משנה, Mishna, because this
now גמרא's Gemara not going to discuss how we know all these
people get סקילה, skila, because we already just discussed it, right? Because
it was all the דמיהם בם demeihem bam issue. What it's going
to do is it's going to hone in on the individual cases,
and going to start with this debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
and the חכמים Chachamim of whether a mother is also the prohibition
of a father's wife. So let's take a look. תניא, Tanya, we
learn in a ברייתא. Braisa.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר, omer
אם לא הייתה אמו ראויה לאביו אינו חייב אלא משום האם בלבד.
im lo hayesa imo reuia le'aviv eino chayav ela mishum ha'eim bilvad.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of the ברייתא Braisa is a much
more narrow debate than רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of the משנה. Mishna.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of the משנה Mishna says a mother is
never in the category of father's wife. Father's wife means stepmother, it
doesn't mean mother. Okay, in the ברייתא, Braisa, he basically says no,
a mother could also be father's wife, but I only argue on
one small point. If the marriage was not appropriate, then you're not
liable for father's wife. In that case, you're not liable. What's a
marriage that's not appropriate? Okay, so מאי אינה ראויה לו? mai eina
reuia lo? What does it mean not fit? אילימא חייבי כריתות וחייבי
מיתות בית דין eillima chayavei krisos vechayavei misos beis din that the
father was married to a woman who's forbidden to him for כרת
kares or מיתת בית דין, misas beis din, you know, he's married
to a relative for example, so then the reason then you're not
חייב chayav liable for father's wife is because the marriage wasn't binding,
because they might have gone through some ceremony, but she's not the
father's wife, the marriage isn't binding in those cases. So מכלל דרבנן
סברי michlal deRabbanan savri would that mean that the Rabbis would hold
אע"ג דאינה ראויה לו af al gav de'eina reuia lo even if
it's not fit and it's not a binding marriage? How could that
be? הרי לית קידושין בגווה harei leis kiddushin begavah the marriage isn't
even binding. So they can't be arguing about that case. Of course,
if the marriage isn't binding, you're not liable for father's wife. אלא
חייבי לאוין ela chayavei lavin
fine. We're not talking about, we're talking about something that's prohibited only
by a simple negative prohibition, like a ממזר. mamzer. So the father
was married to a woman who was a ממזרת, mamzeres, or the
father was a ממזר, mamzer, whatever it was. Okay, in that
case, he said, since they shouldn't be married, even though they're, then
you're not liable for father's wife. So now one minute, so but
why is that if the marriage is binding? So we're going to
say, רבי יהודה סבר לה כרבי עקיבא, Rabbi Yehuda savar lah k'Rabbi
Akiva, he holds like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva דאמר אין קידושין תופסין
בחייבי לאוין. de'amar ein kiddushin tofsin bechayavei lavin. There's a whole discussion
elsewhere that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that even by a simple
negative prohibition, if the marriage is prohibited, it's not binding, even if
it's a simple negative prohibition. So in the end, what רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda just saying is I think in certain cases the marriage
isn't binding and you're not liable for father's wife. And the Rabbis
say, well we think in those cases the marriage is binding and
you are liable. So it's really not even a debate about the
prohibition of father's wife, it's just a debate about in what cases
is marriage binding or not. Okay, so that's a different type of
a debate than is implied in our משנה. Mishna. מתיב רב אושעיא,
maseiv Rav Oshaiya, now רב אושעיא Rav Oshaiya challenged this idea that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds that by negative prohibitions the marriage is
not binding. איסור מצוה ואיסור קדושה, issur mitzvah ve'issur kedushah, if you
have a woman that is forbidden to the brother-in-law, the brother died,
is there a מצוה mitzvah of ייבום, yibum, but she's forbidden to
the brother-in-law because of a prohibition deriving from a מצוה mitzvah or
a prohibition deriving from holiness? חולצת ולא מתייבמת. choletzes velo misyabemes. You
do חליצה chalitza not ייבום. yibum. If it was prohibited to the
brother with כרת, kares, it was let's say I don't know, his
daughter-in-law or whatever the case might be, okay, in that type of
whatever it would be, some relative, okay, then there's no חליצה chalitza
no ייבום, yibum, it's just out of the category. But a woman
who is prohibited to the brother only through a lighter prohibition, it's
not out of the category, you have to do חליצה chalitza but
you're not allowed to do ייבום. yibum. Now who is in this
lighter category? Okay, איסור מצוה issur mitzvah is שניות מדברי סופרים, shnios
mideivrei sofrim, people that are relatives only at the rabbinic level, okay,
like a case would be like a grandmother, okay, that's only a
rabbinic, it's an extension of the biblical idea of the mother. So
that's, so if it's only rabbinically prohibited but biblically allowed, so you
still have to do, you know, you're still obligated, so you do
חליצה, chalitza, you don't do ייבום. yibum. And what's, and ואמאי קרו
להו איסור מצוה? ve'amai karu lehu issur mitzvah? Now the גמרא Gemara
inserts, the first line was the משנה's Mishna line, the next line
is the גמרא's Gemara insertion, you see by the shift to Aramaic
by the way, ואמאי קרו להו איסור מצוה? ve'amai karu lehu issur
mitzvah? שמצוה לשמוע דברי חכמים, shemitzvah lishmoa divrei chachamim, because it's a
מצוה mitzvah to listen to the Rabbis, okay?
So that's rabbinic, rabbinic prohibitions. Now what's איסור קדושה issur kedushah that
you do חליצה chalitza not ייבום? yibum? אלמנה לכהן גדול, גרושה וחלוצה
לכהן הדיוט. almanah lekohen gadol, grushah vachaluza lekohen hedyos. Something that derives
from somebody's כהן kohen status, okay? An אלמנה almanah to a כהן
גדול kohen gadol which is a negative prohibition, a כהן גדול kohen
gadol marrying a widow, or a כהן גדול kohen gadol marrying... a
כהן kohen marrying a גרושה. grushah. גרושה *Gerusha*. Okay,
that's a biblical prohibition, but it's not an איסור כרת *Issur Kareis*,
it's only a negative prohibition, and a negative one deriving from the
קדושה *Kedusha* status. דאמאי קרו ליה *De-amai karu lei* איסור קדושה *Issur
Kedusha* דכתיב קדושים יהיו לאלהיהם *de-chtiv Kedoshim yihiyu l'Eloheihem*. Fine, so that
is those women, they're not completely out of the category, you have
to do חליצה *Chalitza*, you don't do ייבום *Yibum*. Why is this
relevant for us? Because of the next line. דתניא עלה *De-tanya alah*,
we taught on this a ברייתא *Braita*, רבי יהודה מחליף חילופי *Rabbi
Yehuda machlif chilufei*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* switches the terms. He completely
agrees to the הלכה *Halacha*, but he says no, איסור מצוה *Issur
Mitzvah* means the כהונה *Kehuna* types of prohibitions, and איסור קדושה *Issur
Kedusha* means the rabbinic prohibitions. Okay, no big deal, it's all just
a nomenclature issue. But what interests us is that רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* seems to acknowledge that קידושין *Kiddushin* is possible by these women,
because if קידושין *Kiddushin* would not be binding by them, the assumption
would be you wouldn't even have to do חליצה *Chalitza*, they'd be
totally out of the category. People, you got that? Right? So he's
acknowledging that there are these women who are prohibited because of a
גרושה *Gerusha* to a כהן *Kohen*, a negative prohibition, and because they're
enough in the category, you do חליצה *Chalitza*, you don't do ייבום
*Yibum*. But if he said קידושין *Kiddushin* wouldn't work, you wouldn't even
do חליצה *Chalitza*, they'd be out of the category. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, so רבי יהודה
מחליף *Rabbi Yehuda machlif*. So the גמרא *Gemara*, I see I read
the... it's a פירוש *peirush* of רבינו נסים *Rabbeinu Nissim* מחליף *machlif*.
רבי יהודה מחליף *Rabbi Yehuda machlif*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* switches it.
חילופי הוא דמחליף *Chilufei hu de-machlif*, so he switches it, but he
agrees in principle, חליצה בעי *Chalitza ba'ei*, he still needs חליצה *Chalitza*
for these women. ואי סלקא דעתך רבי יהודה כרבי עקיבא סבירא ליה
*Ve-i salka daitach Rabbi Yehuda ke-Rabbi Akiva sevira lei*, if he felt
like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that by a negative prohibition קידושין *Kiddushin*
wasn't binding, מכדי *mechdi*, let's take a look. חייבי לאוין לרבי עקיבא
כחייבי כריתות דמו *Chayavei lavin l'Rabbi Akiva ke-chayavei krisos damu*. So he
basically treats them all in the same category, so as חייב כרת
*chayav kareis*. וחייבי כריתות לאו בני חליצה וייבום נינהו *ve-chayavei krisos lav
bnei chalitza ve-yibum ninhu*, חייבי כריתות *chayavei krisos* because קידושין *Kiddushin* isn't
binding, they're completely out of the category, they don't get חליצה *Chalitza*.
So רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* should, if he really held that way,
these women shouldn't be getting חליצה *Chalitza* either. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, לדבריו דתנא קמא קאמר ולאו סבירא ליה *Le-divrav de-Tanna Kama ka-amar
ve-lav sevira lei*. It's fine, he's saying according to the תנא קמא
*Tanna Kama*, which is so funny. He's saying, look guys, I really
think that these women you don't even have to do חליצה *Chalitza*
for, because I think קידושין *Kiddushin* isn't binding. But according to you
that you think you have to do חליצה *Chalitza* for them, I
think you got the terms wrong. You should be calling the כהונה
*Kehuna* category איסור מצוה *Issur Mitzvah*, and the rabbinic category איסור קדושה
*Issur Kedusha*. It's such a funny thing to be debating. If you
don't even agree to the הלכה *Halacha*, why are you nitpicking about
what terms that you use? Anyway, that's what the גמרא *Gemara* says.
So this is one way of reading it. According to the ברייתא
*Braita*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is not fundamentally disagreeing about the prohibition
of mother's father's wife, he's just saying I think that there are
some categories, חייבי לאוין *chayavei lavin*, women that are forbidden because of
a negative prohibition, that it wouldn't be a binding marriage and therefore
it wouldn't be father's wife. Okay? But let's just read one more
line and then we'll end with this for today, because now the
גמרא'ס *Gemara's* going to shift and now we're going to put the
ברייתא *Braita* aside and go back to פשט *pshat* of the משנה
*Mishna*. Okay, so let's just read that shift. כי אתא רב יצחק
*Ki ata Rav Yitzchak*, when רב יצחק *Rav Yitzchak* came from ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, תני כדתנן *tani ke-detnan*. He had a ברייתא *Braita*
that was not limiting the debate about this case of not fit
for the father, but was a more basic debate, like our משנה
*Mishna*. רבי יהודה אומר אינו חייב אלא משום האם בלבד *Rabbi Yehuda
omer eino chayav ela mishum ha-eim bilvad*, that there even a normal
case of a mother who is a father's wife, רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says that is not in the father's wife category, that is
only in the mother's category. And now we're going to try to
figure out the reason, we'll read just one answer and tomorrow we'll
continue to see other explanations why it's not in that category. טעמא
מאי *Ta-ama mai*? What is the reason that it's not also father's
wife? אמר אביי דאמר קרא אמך היא *Amar Abaye de-amar kra imcha
hi*. The verse says אמך היא *imcha hi*, that it says a
man should not sleep whatever with his mother. אמך היא לא תגלה
ערותה *Imcha hi lo tegaleh ervatah*. She's your mother, don't uncover her
nakedness. So the emphasis אמך היא *imcha hi*, she's your mother, משום
אמא אתה מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו משום אשת אב *mishum ima atah
mechayvo ve-ei atah mechayvo mishum eshes av*, that the only category that
applies to her is the category of mother, no other category applies
to her. So a woman who is this man's mother is only
looked at through the lens of mother and not through any other
lens. Okay? So we'll continue with this tomorrow to see if this
serves as the basis for רבי יהודה'ס *Rabbi Yehuda's* position that a
mother is not in the אשת אב *eshes av* category. All right.